Do you remember how many classes do we have
for bandit algorithms, 4. you will try okay
fine because the rate at which I am going
I will probably need one more class just to
finish the two proofs I wanted to do today
so which should mean that I would need one
more extra class for finishing all of bandits
did we do 4 classes last year 6 yeah I think
I we did we even had visiting faculty give
a talk hmm...okay. We have 4 oh good fine
then I am not too bad okay.
So instead of writing the cumbersome 2 ln
n by s all over right so I am defining that
as Cns okay then if I write Cn-1s it is ln
of n-1 divided by s and then I can do C n,
s + 1 so on so forth right I can just like
a function just substitute that will make
my life little easier right so the goal now
as I mentioned earlier is to upper bound this
expectation right so I will never play a suboptimal
arm more than this many times okay that is
essentially what we are trying to show okay
so one other notation I will just adopt the
notation used in the proof here even though
we introduced a different notation in the
previous class for the same thing okay it
makes it little easier for me.
This notation indicates a I mean it denotes
a random variable corresponding to that indicator
right so this is a random variable whose value
1 if I t equal to i whose value is 0 if I
t is not equal to i okay so whatever is this
I will put in some kind of events here later
right so if I t equal to i, then what does
it mean it means that okay fine I apologize
for the confusion this yeah so when I say
I n equal to i, okay it means that at time
n I played arm i, right so if this the whole
expression within curly braces will be one
if at time at n I played arm i, it will be
0 if at time n I played some other arm not
i okay so there are couple of things which
we can observe about this so at any instant
I n equal to i will be 1 for some i for everything
else it will be 0.
Right because at very time instant I can play
only arm and at every time instance I will
play at least 1 arm okay so it will be 1 for
one of the arms for everything else it will
be 0 okay this yeah the paper is not really
the most accessible of papers out there right
so if you are going to read it on your own
you will have to do some some work okay so
things are not I mean they just assume that
you are all really really smart people reading
the paper so since some of the gaps you will
have to fill in yourself right I am just doing
one of the proofs in the papers so if you
want to read the rest of the paper and understand
all the theorems and all the algorithms that
they describe in the paper.
So you will need to do some additional work
okay so L is some arbitrary positive integer
so I start off by saying this.. okay so the
number of times I have played arm i up til
the nth instant will be one which I get from
the initialization plus k+1 because obviously
I couldn't have played that arm again in the
first K times right in the first K times I
will play each arm only once right so arm
i also I would have played once so in the
first K trials the summation will be just
1 so I just have that 1 there and from the
k + 1 th trial till the nth trial, I add the
number of times this variable is 1 what does
it mean number of times I have taken arm i
right so I m will be, I m equal to i will
be 1 whenever I take arm i so I just sum this
up so that so that the number of times I played
arm i is what I get right.
Is that fine, this expression is fine okay
this is the only directly intuitive part that
we have here so after this no no after this
whatever you do, these are all standard tricks
that people play to bound random variables
okay so to actually tell you about the general
techniques for all of this, I recommend you
take the ATTOC course because about third
of the course is all about how to do proofs
like this right how many of you have done
ATTOC already advanced techniques in theoretical
computer science theory of computation.
Okay that is a course that Jayalal Sarma teaches
in the CS department so it is very relevant
to lot of ML researches because more lot of
machine learning has become like randomized
algorithms right so if people teach you how
to analyse randomized algorithms you can take
the same ideas and use them in analyzing machine
learning algorithms as well so lot of the
tools that are developed there are useful
here and many of the things that we do here
right essentially have their roots in the
kind of analysis that people do for randomized
algorithms okay.
Any way we so we will start off by doing that
so I have an arbitrary number l okay I say
that okay fine let us assume that I have played
the arm l times okay then let us start counting
right so assuming that uptil the m-1 th step
okay I have l or greater than l right only
then I will count the arm pull so at some
point I have discovered that I have pulled
arm i okay should I add it to my count or
not what I do I will go head and look at the
cumulative count so far if the cumulative
count is l or higher I will add it to my count
if it is below l I do not add it to my count
because I am anyway starting my count from
l okay.
So this is slightly different way of doing
that this is saying that I will start the
count from some arbitrary number given that
I have taken that arbitrary number already
right so later on we will essentially now
are going to bound this expression assuming
that at least l times I have taken the arm
right and then we will derive a bound for
l so that we get whatever probability we want
okay so that is the idea behind doing this
so this I can now derive a bound for this
assuming I have done at least l times right
then I will go back and find what is that
value of l so that I get whatever probabilities
I want right whatever guarantees I want I
will go and find that l okay that's essentially
what we are going to do here.
Okay I just need more notation here right
this let me try this any way so when am I
going to take arm i right when will I take
arm i when arm i has the highest where is
this thing right when arm i has the highest
value for this quantity right when will I
take arm i when if that has the highest quantity
among all the arms.
Specifically I will take arm i only when Q
plus C so that root term is now C right that
root term there is what I have written as
C so I will take arm i only when Q plus that
C term is greater than Q of a star plus the
C terms corresponding to a star.
Yes that is why I have my lesser than or equal
to here see at specifically this should be
true right in fact it has to be larger than
everything else right but at least it has
to be larger than a star correct so it has
to be larger than every other action but like
he rightly pointed out so this is a larger
set than when I will actually be taking the
action but that is okay because I am only
trying to upper bound it right I am not trying
to give an exact number because trying to
give an exact number makes it too involved
right I am just trying to give an upper bound
so I'm saying very specifically I am looking
at the best arm I am saying that this should
be better than the best arm.
At least right so anything else we need to
have we will still need to have this right
that condition is also there so I will put
that condition back in right what does this
curly bracket mean it is the curly bracket
is a random variable that indicates it will
have a value of 1 if the expression within
the curly bracket is true it will have value
of 0 when the expression within the curly
brackets is false so essentially this summation
counts how may times this inequality becomes
true after I has been taken l times right
so that is what we did here right so this
counting is whatever we are doing here is
after l times i has been taken because l I
have added here as a count so likewise I am
counting the number of times this inequality
becomes true after i has been taken l times.
So this is essentially what I have so far
right. Where? Here, this entire thing there
is a seat vacant here and there is another
seat vacant here if you want to move as well
you can see everything you guys are all fine
right you don't want to complain because I
will tell you there is a whole row vacant
here no can't you see what I have written
or don't you understand what I have written
well subscripts become small right if you
write them large then it becomes confusing
so that is C m-1 for people who cannot read
it I am reading it out that is C m -1 , T
a star of m-1.
That is basically the number of times I have
played a star uptil the m-1 th point right
note that I do not have to know this because
I do not know what is a star right this is
just the there but you know that there exists
a a-star right and I know that my i has to
have a better whatever that quantity than
a-star right so its just that right I do not
know I do not need to know which is a star
okay just do not get confused by the fact
that I am using a star in the proof right
did you get that C m-1 , T a-star m-1 and
this is C m-1, T i of m-1. No a-star is the
true true best action
which you do not know anything about right
because for regret we have to compare against
the true best action right so we are comparing
against the true best action right okay so
far so good people can people who could not
see heard me right and people understand what
is going on right so now we will I'm shifting
over here.
My God for writing one line I am talking for
10 minutes man. I really need to have an additional
index for the Q-function for us to say these
things, right. What I wrote there is m-1,
so the Q-function at step m-1 okay, I really
need that additional thing because Q keeps
changing over time right so I need to know
at what stage I am talking about the Q-function,
so at that point I am talking about the Q-function
at the m-1 th stage, right. Remember that
the Q-function at the m-1 stage can be the
same as the Q-function at the m th stage if
I had not taken the action previously.
At the m-1 th stage if I am not taking action
a or action i, then at the mth stage also
the Q-function of action i will be the same,
it wouldn't have changed, right just you have
to be careful about how you interpret the
index and I hope I also do not mess it up
when I do these things here. No so we do read
the different interpretation for and I do
need an additional notation I apologize for
that
because we need to what we need to insert
into this bound here.
is the number of time I have taken a-star
so far, right what I need to insert into this
bound, is the number of times I have taken
a-star so far which is T a-star m-1 right
and so it become a little cumbersome now this
can be is this will be T a-star of s okay
fine we can get away with that. This is a
little weird expression so what I am saying
here is okay take the minimum of this expression
okay over all time instants 0 to m.
Take the maximum of this expression right
for all time instants l to m okay and look
at the number of times one will be higher
than the other, right. This will be a over
count of that event this is clear right but
here I am talking about this quantity being
higher than this quantity at that particular
instant right I am talking about some time
m-1 where the quantity for a-star was lesser
than the quantity for i.
I am talking about sometime instant m-1 at
which this happened here what I am talking
about, okay at a time m-1 right I look at
all the a-star values I have had in the previous
time steps okay, I will take the least of
that, right and I will take all the i values
Qi values I have had in the previous time
steps I will take the max of that okay.
If the max of this is greater than the min
of that then I will count that as 1, right
so can you convince yourself that, that event
will certainly be counted right because at
that instant the value is already greater
so obviously the max will be greater than
the min right so if this is not the min, right
the min should be lesser than this and if
this is not the max, then the max should be
greater than this.
So if this value is greater than this value
then the some quantity greater than this value
will certainly be greater than some quantity
lesser than this value right you can see that
right, so this is just a over count of that
event, right why am I writing this over count?
Because it makes it easier for me to, sorry,
now that is the event right the curly brackets
makes it easier for me to write a expression.
Yeah what is it, one second I will come let
me finish. yeah 0 less than s less than m,
l less than or equal to Si less than or equal
to m because l because I have that condition
there right I have to have taken this at least
l times, so the first l times what happens
I do not worry so I will remove that right
so only after that I am worried about, but
this will be an over count okay this will
be an over count of that. So little tricky
here so now the proof actually assumes that
at this point, okay.
I have taken this at least s times not T a-star
s times okay, it is mainly because there is
the notation translation problem but we will
see we will work with this and then I will
probably adjust the results later, right.
But if you are reading the proof I am just
telling you there is a mismatch in the notation
that we have used so far, okay. But this is
the neat trick that we have downed at, right.
We have taken rid of all the Min Max and everything,
right,
So what are we doing here so assume that the
Min occurs at some index right let us call
that index, I do not know p, p1 let us assume
that the Max occurs at some index say p2 right,
so now what I am doing here is I am summing
over all possible indices for a-star and I
am summing over all possible indices for i,
correct. So the combination p1, p2 will occur
somewhere because I am summing over all possible
indices, right.
At some point I would have used p1 for s,
and p2 for Si, correct because I am summing
over all possible indices right so what was
p1, p1 was the one for which this minimum
was achieved p2 was the one for which this
maximum was achieved, so when I am summing
over s at some point s will have p1 at some
point Si will have p2 right, at that point
this expression will surely be true because
I know from the Min and Max argument that
we had earlier that will be true.
So I will certainly be counting this right
I will be over counting I will be counting
other things also but I will certainly be
counting this, so essentially so far we have
not lost anything we are essentially still
maintaining at as Upper bound okay, so we
started off with this event right now we have
done a lot of simplifications and kept loosening
the bound, this was a strict equality and
there was nothing here, right.
This was strict equality no approximation
here, so from there at every step I am essentially
counting a larger and larger event, now the
thing is I have come to a point where I have
a simple enough expression right that I can
try to bound directly now, okay. So you can
start thinking you know this kind of should
lead you to the Chernoff-Hoeffding bound I
can use the bound, Chernoff Hoeffding bound
to try and bound this expression.
This is simple enough expression, okay. So
if this is true, okay this is true when can
this happen? So my claim is this can be true
if one of several conditions hold right, so
this can be true if, okay this can be true
if I am either I am grossly under estimating
my optimal actions value, right. So this is
my optimal actions estimate now this is the
true value right so the true value minus the
confidence bound.
Or the other way around think about it, right.
This Qs a-star plus the confidence bound is
less than the true value that means I am grossly
under estimating the true value that is one
thing right. So that could be one condition
under which this could be true what could
be another condition you are grossly over
estimating the ith value you are getting it,
so either I have to make a big mistake for
my Q star, a-star or I have to make a big
mistake the other way for my i right you see
that, right.
So I have to either come very down from a
true Q star value I mean a Q star, a-star
or I have to be much above my normal value
otherwise this is not going to happen, right.
So second condition is, okay. Or when can
it happen without me grossly over estimating
or under estimating it? When the true values
are close right if the two values the a-star
value and the i value are close to each other
then I really do not have to grossly under
estimate these things.
So it is possible that I still could make
errors, right. So essentially the other condition
is right so I have my twice my I take the
confidence interval right so I have a confidence
interval add here I will have a confidence
interval I will add from that side, right.
So I will add a confidence interval right
so I am taking twice the confidence interval
from my lower value right, from the lower
value I take twice the confidence interval.
And if the upper value that is the optimal
actions value lies within that right then
I can make a mistake without making a gross
error also, right essentially I am saying
that these two are close together, right.
And close is a relative term close is defined
in terms of the current uncertainty I have,
right. Because this is going to change every
time I take an action this is going to become
smaller and smaller, right.
So at the beginning of the learning this can
be fairly large so I can still make a mistake
right even if the means are slightly far apart,
right. So do you see the 3 conditions one
of this at least will have to be satisfied
for this event to become true, second one
says I mean second one is easy man, so the
first one says okay I have my Q of a-star
and I have my confidence bound this is the
first one okay and the true Q star, a-star
is there, okay.
That means I have grossly under estimated
my Q star a-star this is one condition, so
the second condition says this is Q of i right
and this is Q star of i, so grossly overestimated
by Q star of i that is essentially what the
second condition says so this is Qi is greater
than Q star i plus the confidence bound so
this is the confidence bound so Q star i plus
this confidence bound will be only till here,
right. But Q i is greater than that.
Whats that, No, no this is yet another condition
that can hold right when both of these do
not hold also I could still be making a mistake
right I could still this could still be one
if the true means or not far apart with respect
to this error bar I have. See basically what
I am saying is, a true Q star could be somewhere
here right but I still can make a mistake
because it is too close. So probably draw
all this pictures and put it somewhere permanently.
Because every time I seem to be re-creating
these pictures, right. So I have the first
thing I said okay the Q * is somewhere there
right I make a mistake right so and then I
have this guy right so its possible for me
to make an error, right and then the other
case was okay this the true Q was somewhere
here it is possible for me to make a mistake
right this third case says no none of this
really need to happen, right the true Q stars
could be well within the bounds right, but
given the current uncertainty I have in my
Q of i right, so the true means are not so
far apart right this this uncertainty cannot
overwhelm it right the true means are actually
within the uncertainty. Therefore, I could
still make a mistake so the first condition
is not true the second condition is not true
but I still made the mistake, okay.
So people have all of this expression everyone
has in their notebooks people who are writing
notes, people who are not writing notes you
have this in your memory, okay because I am
going to erase it but I am going to need it
again, okay so I want all of you to remember
this.
Okay, so let us look at 1, so I want to look
at the probability that a-star so I want to
bound that probability, right so can I do
that remember I told you Sn is capital Q,
I told you mu is Q star right, so we have
that already right, if you remember when I
wrote down the Hoeffding Chernoff bounds,
I told you the comparison right, I told you
that Sn is capital Q, mu is Q star so you
have those there, right. So essentially then
your epsilon becomes C m right and my bound
is e power minus 2 epsilon squared n right,
and what is Cn so it is 2lnn by s squared.
Plug it in, simplify it and tell me what is
the answer? So what is your n there, now what
is the n that you have you to plug in to the
expression, s this is where the thing became
a little messy because the paper uses s as
the, I mean they introduce an additional notation,
right but I did not use that I try to use
the T star, T a-star notation itself, so it
becomes T a-star of s that is the thing that
you have to plug in, okay so simplify it and
tell me what is the answer.
So I plug in T a-star of s here m here right,
and then I have to square it basically that
is my epsilon that will get squared, right
so my T a-star of s and my T a-star of s get
cancelled, right I will get ln m come on,
after all that we have done so far you could
do this simplification easily enough just
substitute this into that and then cancel
things out and tell me what is happening.
1 by m power 4 right, so essentially this
will be less than or equal to okay, so what
about the second term okay hmm...phew, what
about the third term okay, here is where we
are going to use our mysterious l right, what
did l, what did I introduce l for I said that
hey, I have done so many number of trials
already, okay I am only looking at these events
after that many number of times I have taken
arm i, right.
So I am going to make the following statement
if I have taken sufficient number of trials
initially okay, if I have taken sufficient
number of pulls of arm i initially this event
will never happen that is what I am claiming,
right this is rather easy to see right, so
what do we have, we have q star a-star minus
Q star i minus 2 Cm.. okay right. So essentially
I am saying that my Ti Si is at least this
much, right so that is what this means right
okay, when I say l is equal to this much that
means the number of times I have taken arm
i is at least this much.
If you remember my Si summation starts from
l right, I consider Si only from l so if say
l is this so that means my Ti Si is at least
this much, correct go and plug this into my
C ns expression.
So if my s is this much, at least this much,
so what do I get, I get 2 by 8 ln m and my
delta i squared will go up so ln m, ln m will
get cancelled, right so 2 by 8 will become
1 by 4 that is half, half into delta i right,
so half and 2 will get cancelled I will essentially
get delta i, right so this expression will
become.
Right and what is this equal to, so for any
value of l greater than this, this quantity
will be greater than 0 that means this inequality
will never hold, correct do people see that,
you want me to do that again, yes okay, so
I am saying l is going to be at least this
much so then if you remember my Ti Si that
the Si summation is starting from l, I am
assuming that at least l times I have taken
this already, right.
So I am assuming you have taken this l times
already so what I will do is I will plug the,
this value for the number of times I have
taken this already right this value, so I
will plug in 8 ln m right this is C m,s right
so in this case look at the expression m,
this so this will be ln m right I am plugging
in here instead of s, I will plug in 8 times
ln m divided by delta i squared right, ln
m, ln m will get cancelled so 2 by 8 will
become 1 by 4 and divide by delta i squared
will go up right, so I will basically get
root of delta i squared by 4 which is delta
i by 2, right.
So I will come and plug in delta i by 2 here,
2 and 2 will get cancelled I will essentially
end up getting delta i here, so that is what
I have written here. So and by definition
of delta i this expression is 0, right and
for values larger I mean if I take the action
i more times then this will essentially become
greater than 0 and therefore that inequality
that I wanted will never hold, if I have taken
l at least, if I have taken action i at least
l number of times where l is given by that
expression.
The third condition will never hold, okay
so the probability of the third condition
holding is 0 if l is greater than this, right.
So now what happens so the probability of
this whole thing happening is upper bounded
by just two times this probability right,
just add these events up so we are still not
done. Where are we, so we are bounding the
expected value of that thing right, so we
have expected value of, so and I am going
to ask you to write this out here okay.
So this is lesser than or equal to 8ln m by
delta i squared because that is l plus these
summation terms that we had earlier right,
and I am substituting a specific value for
l here okay, then what will be the internal
term here. Remember, we had this random variable
which could take values of 1 or 0 so what
is the expected value of the random variable
is just a probability of it being 1, right
so there are only two of those things right.
So the probability of this event plus the
probability of this event, right that is basically
it so I am not writing down this because these
expressions are going to take a long right
so the probability of this event plus the
probability of that event so in which our
case is just m-4, m power -4 that is essentially,
right so it is clear. So you see how that
came about, right so here this was the random
variable right. Now once I took the expectation
so I can replace that random variable with
the probability of it being 1 that will be
the expectation of that random variable, okay
is it fine so replace that with the probability
of it being 1 is upper bounded by m -4, m
-4 and that is basically here, okay great.
So this summation okay, I am going to declare
it to converge to 1 plus pi squared by 3 okay,
you can its little involved thing but it is
pure algebra again I mean you can work it
out, okay or I mean this is a standard relation
you can look it up also, right so that is
basically what we have. So this is kind of
see that this is going to because this is
going to be a diminishing sum so it is going
to converge to a limit, right and so what
is really interesting is this part, right
it is some constant whatever it is that it
converges to it is not really of interest
you know not really of great interest what
is really of interest is this 8 ln n by delta
i, right.
Because this is the one where you are going
to get messed up a lot because it has the
ln n term right, and it also has your delta
i squared, right but this is the only expected
value of T i n, right you have to multiply
it by delta i to get the total regret and
you have to sum over all i, right so that
is essentially the thing that we have finally
that expression that I erased here that is
what you will end up with that is why I said
keep that in your mind because that is the
final expression you are going to end up with,
right.
This is for each arm this is for one suboptimal
arm, right this is the total number of times
you have played it right that is all we have
derived now, so the regret due to that suboptimal
arm will be delta i times this number so that
is why the delta i squared goes to delta i
in the denominator in the original expression
if you flip back and you look at the original
expression we had a delta i here and we also
had a 1 plus pi squared by 3 into delta i.
but this is for one arm, so you have to do
this for all the suboptimal arms basically
that is why your summation is over all i which
is not optimal, okay great.
So this is you have done with UCB and you
have shown that UCB's regret is bounded and
what is the nice thing we have shown here
is that the regret grows as ln n right, and
there is a result from the 80s which tells
us that you cannot have a regret optimizing
algorithm that does better than ln n, right
what you can try to improve on is the 8, right
this
is also impossible to get rid of, the delta
i is also impossible to get rid of you cannot
say that I will, I mean if the arms are close
in reward right, it becomes hard to eliminate
the bad arms, right. If they are far away
in reward then you can quickly figure out
which are the bad arms but if the arms are
close in reward and it becomes harder to figure
out so those things are always there.
So those are essential components to it so
basically people fiddle around with that 8,
okay and yeah so that is essentially the lot
of work that happens in regret optimality
so I will have to stop here because we have
reached 5 o clock I do not know if how many
of you noticed it so if you have not I will
take that as I kept you successfully engrossed,
but if people were just biding their time
to leave well I apologize for keeping here
for so long, but I needed to finish this right,
I could not have stopped half way through
and then start in the next class with 3 summations
or something, right.
So in the next class right, so we will look
at the last optimality criterion I was talking
about which was PAC optimality, okay.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved